Guide to the George A. Clark. Fur Seal Controversy Papers, 1892-1969
Department of Special Collections
George A. Clark. Fur Seal Controversy Papers,
1892-1969
Special Collections M118
Clark, George A.
3 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions:
None.
Provenance:
Gift of George A. Clark.
Acquisition Information:
These papers were originally received as part of the David Starr Jordan Papers, which were part of the Stanford Collection. They were transferred to the Manuscripts Collection in July 1965.
BIOGRAPHY
George A. Clark, born in Eden Prairie, Minnesota in 1864, graduated from the University of Minnesota and served as Academic Secretary of Stanford University from 1891-1918. He was Secretary of the Bering Sea Fur Seal Commission (1896-1898) and was involved in the special investigation of seal herds for the Bureau of Fisheries in 1909 and 1912. He died 27 April 1918.
SCOPE AND CONTENT
This collection consists largely of Correspondence to and from George A. Clark and David Starr Jordan. There are also a number of articles (manuscript, typescript and printed) by G. A. Clark and others on the fur seal controversy. Also included are four notebooks on seals and photographs of seals and seal islands. The bulk of the collection dates from 1892 to 1918; there is one added item dated 1969.
The Correspondence has a number of letters to and from: Alfred Fraser, H. M. Smith, H. W. Elliott, Barton W. Evermann, E. A. Hayes, Charles Nagel, W. I. Lembkey, E. N. Lomasney, G. M. Hitchcock, George M. Bowers, W. E. Reynolds, D. H. Dunlap, William T. Hornaday, O. H. Townsend, M. C. Marsh, William C. Redfield, W. O. Stillman, Minnie Maddern Fiske, John H. Rothermel, Jamus Judge, James McKeen Cattell, M. Colby, and William Gordon. There are also one or two letters from Henry Cabot Lodge, William Kent, John D. Works, Robert M. La Follette, and Woodrow Wilson.
CONTAINER LIST
- Typescripts (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1. ÒResume of Discussion at the International Fur Seal ConferenceÓ Washington, D.C. 1897.
  - 2. ÒThe Fur Seal Islands of AlaskaÓ [1897]
  - 3. Report of the Recent Fur Seal Conference [1897]
  - 4. Journal March 1, 1897
  - 5. Journal March 4, 1897
  - 6. Journal March 12, 1897
  - 7. [cont. journal] n.d. beginning ÒMr. Elliott remarksÉÓ
  - 8. Memorandum Regarding The Fur Seals
- Typescripts (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1. ÒInterview with Mr. W. ElliottÓ [1897]
  - 2. ÒInterview with Mr. Homes of the Boston HeraldÓ [1897]
  - 3. ÒThe Future of the Alaska Fur Seal IndustryÓ [1897]
  - 4. ÒProtocols of the International Fur Seal ConferenceÓ [1897]
  - 5. ÒThe Scientific Expert and the Bering Sea ControversyÓ
  - 6. ÒThe Fur Seals and Fur Seal IndustriesÓ
  - 7. Mr. ChamberlainÕs Letter
  - 8. Memorandum
  - 9. ÒThe SealsÓ
  - 10. ÒFur Seal Skins from various sources 1743-1897Ó
- Correspondence and Misc. Articles (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1. Correspondence to Clark and David Starr Jordan 1903-1908
  - 2. ÒSenator Shiveley and The Fur SealsÓ
  - 3. ÒA Correction of FactÓ
- Correspondence and Misc. Articles (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1. Correspondence Nov. 14, 1910 -Dec. 19, 1910
  - 2. ÒMr. Henry W. Elliott and The Fur SealsÓ
  - 3. Correspondence Dec. 11, 1910 -Sept. 26, 1911
- Correspondence Oct. 4, 1911 -Mar. 30, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence and Misc. Articles (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1. ÒSuspension of land killing in 1891-93 resulted in great injury to the Seal Herd.Ó
  - 2. Correspondence Apr. 3, 1912 -May 14, 1912
  - 3. ÒClose season detrimental in proportion to its lengthÓ
  - 4. "Depletion of Fur Seal Herd caused by killing female seals in the sea, not by killing surplus males on land"
  - 5. "Die Robben und ihre Beschtzung" by Von D.S. Jordan and G.A. Clark
  - 6. Correspondence W.O. Stillman - Clark Dec. 1909
  - 7. "Fur Trade Review Feb. 1911"
  - 8. Correspondence Mar. 23, 1912 -July 27, 1912
  - 9. "Army and Navy Register" July 27, 1912
  - 10. "Fur Seal Convention remarks by Benjamin F. Shiveley and William P. Dillingham" Aug. 15, 1912
  - 11. Science: "The Fur Seal Census" typescript ms. with corrections and published copy
  - 12. Correspondence Aug. 14, 1912 -Nov. 1, 1912
- Correspondence and Misc. Articles (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - 1. "Fight to Preserve Fur Seals" Chicago Interocean Nov. 10, 1912
  - 2. Correspondence Nov. 11, 1912 -Nov. 27, 1912
  - 3. Report of House of Rep. committee hearings
  - 4. Correspondence Nov. 29, 1912 -Dec. 3, 1912
  - 5. "The Truth About the Fur Seals of the Pribilof Islands" by D.S. Jordan Dec. 3, 1912
  - 6. Correspondence Dec. 3, 1912 -Jan 3, 1913
  - 7. Congressional Act of Aug. 24, 1912 amended Jan. 3, 1913
  - 8. Correspondence Jan 3, 1913 -Jan. 16, 1913
- Correspondence and Misc. Articles (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - 1. Correspondence to D.S. Jordan from Woodrow Wilson, Jan. 14, 1913
  - 2. "Objectionable Fur Seal Legislation" from CollierÕs Weekly, Jan 16, 1913
  - 3. "A Wasteful and Useless Measure" from Saturday Evening Post, Jan. 16, 1913
  - 4. Correspondence Jan. 16, 1913 -Jan. 17, 1913
  - 5. Correspondence Jan. 14, 1913 -Jan. 25, 1913.One signed by Theodore Roosevelt Jan. 23
  - 6. Membership list of the Campfire Club
  - 7. Correspondence Jan. 25, 1913 -Feb. 16, 1913with one from Henry Cabot Lodge on Jan. 29, one from John D. Works on Feb. 4, and three from William Kent on Feb. 1, Feb. 11, and Feb. 15.
- Correspondence and Misc. Articles (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - 1. "The Truth About Russian Sealing"
  - 2. Correspondence Feb. 17, 1913 -Feb. 24, 1913with one from Robert M. LaFollette of Feb. 18.
  - 3. "Repeal the Law Suspending Land Sealing"
  - 4. Correspondence Feb. 25, 1913 -Mar. 10, 1913
  - 5. Correspondence Aug. 9, 1908, Feb. 29, 1908, Mar. 21, 1912, Mar. 8, 1912, and Oct. 16, 1912
  - 6. Correspondence (10) Mar. 10, 1913with one to D.S. Jordan from Woodrow Wilson
  - 7. "VeniaminovÕs remarks on the fur seal and translation of or reference to the same by others"
  - 8. Correspondence Mar. 11, 1913 -Mar. 12, 1913
  - 9. "Memorandum regarding VeniaminovÕs account of fur seals."
  - 10. Correspondence Mar. 12, 1913
- Correspondence and Misc. Articles (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - 1. Correspondence Mar. 15, 1913 -Apr. 15, 1913
  - 2. "Condensed Report of Investigation of Fur Seal Herd for Season of 1912"
  - 3. "Amos Allen"
  - 4. Ms. beginning "From the very opening of theÉ" concerning seals, typescript transl. by Raphael Zon
  - 5. Correspondence Apr. 16, 1913 -Jun. 12, 1913
- Correspondence and Misc. Articles (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - 1. "The Alleged ÔSalvatorsÕ of the Fur Seals"
  - 2. "To Comfort the conscience of the Woman who has a Sealskin"
  - 3. Correspondence June 12, 1913 -Jun. 14, 1913
  - 4. "The Truth About Russian Sealing"
  - 5. First 216 pp. of typescript of "The Fur Seals of the Pribilof Islands" report of Special Investigation 1912 by G. Clark
- Correspondence and Misc. Articles (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - 1. Correspondence June 14, 1913 -Jan. 19, 1914
  - 2. Congressional Committee Report "on expenditures in the Dept. of Commerce" Sat. Jan. 14, 1914
  - 3. "The Fur Seal Census of 1913"
  - 4. "Order of Procedure in Salt House, Village of St. Paul"
  - 5. Letter (21 pp.) to Chairman, Committee on Expenditure, from Clark, Feb. 6, 1914
  - 6. "Condensed Report of Investigation of Fur Seal Herd for Season of 1912"
  - 7. "Dr. Jordan deliberately falsifies the Russian record in re not killing female seals"
  - 8. Published "Investigation of Fur Seal Industry of Alaska"
  - 9. Correspondence Mar. 10, 1914 -Mar. 16, 1914
  - 10. "The Fate of the Fur Seal" by Joseph Collenson
  - 11. Correspondence Mar. 22, 1914 -Mar. 28, 1914
  - 12. "Seal and Seal Fisheries"
  - 13. Correspondence (4) Apr. 2, 1914
  - 14. "The Dept. Attitude of the Leasing System"
- Correspondence and Misc. Articles (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - 1. Correspondence Apr. 2, 1914 -Apr. 20, 1914
  - 2. "The Fur Seal Industry of Alaska" (in shorthand) and typescript (2 copies) and printed copy
  - 3. Correspondence Apr. 20, 1914 -Apr. 23, 1914
  - 4. "The Fur Seal Situation"
  - 5. Correspondence May 13, 1914 -May 28, 1914
  - 6. Correspondence Oct. 22, 1914 -Nov. 10, 1914
  - 7. "The Making of a Fur Seal Census"
  - 8. "The Fur Seal Industry of Alaska"
  - 9. Correspondence Nov. 25, 1914 -Dec. 15, 1914
  - 10. Correspondence May 11, 1915 -June 25, 1915
  - 11. "The Fur Seal Report for 1914"
  - 12. Correspondence Aug. 28, 1915 -Feb. 21, 1916
- Correspondence and Misc. Articles (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - 1. "Those Fur Seal Bones"
  - 2. Correspondence Feb. 29, 1916 -May 29, 1916
  - 3. Typed ms. beginning "SEAL: a term appliedÉ"
  - 4. Clipping May 28, and June 8, 1916
  - 5. Correspondence June 29, 1916 -Aug. 8, 1916and clipping
  - 6. "Mismanagement and waste of public property"
  - 7. Correspondence Aug. 14, 1916 -Oct. 11, 1916
  - 8. "The Census of Fur Seals 1914, 1915"
  - 9. "Fur Seal Mortality"
  - 10. Correspondence Oct. 28, 1916 -Nov. 20, 1916
  - 11. "Notes" - on seals
  - 12. "The Fur Seal Census of 1916"
  - 13. Correspondence Jan. 9, 1917 -June 5, 1917
  - 14. "Two Fur Seal Problems and Their Solution"
  - 15. "The Fur Seal as an Animal" by D.S. Jordan and G.A. Clark
  - 16. For NelsonÕs Cyclopedia "Seals" galley proof
  - 17. "Pelagic Sealing and the Fur Seal Herd"
- Published Material (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - 1. Commercial subjects in high schools. n.d.
  - 2. The scientific expert and the Bering Sea controversy 1899
  - 3. The Bogoslofs. 1906.
  - 4. The much misunderstood fur seals of Bering Sea. 1910.
  - 5. The vocabulary of business Correspondence. 1910.
  - 6. Shorthand - Its educational and practical value. 1911
  - 7. The blood of the nation by David S. Jordan, done in Pitmanic shorthand 1912.
  - 8. The fur seal census. 1912.
  - 9. The Katmai eruption. 1912.
  - 10. Die Roben und ihre Beschtzung. 1912.
  - 11. The Administration of the fur seal service. 1913.
  - 12. The fur seal census for 1913. 1913.
  - 13. Recent fur seal legislation. 1913.
  - 14. Investigation of the fur seal industry of Alaska. 1914.
  - 15. The new fur seal investigation. 1914.
  - 16. Russian versus American sealing. 1914.
  - 17. The fur seal report for 1914. 1915.
  - 18. The problem of the Pribilof Islands. 1915.
  - 19. The census of fur seals, 1914 and 1915. 1916.
  - 20. Conservation and utilization of our fur seal herd. 1916.
  - 21. Those fur seal bones. 1916.
  - 22. The fur seal census of 1916. 1917.
  - 23. Death of George A. Clark. 1918.
- Seal Islands of Alaska - letter from the Secretary of Commerce (with reports by G.A. Clark), July 19, 1911. (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Notebooks (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - 1. by Clark (3) daily records from May 22 -Aug. 9, 1897centering around the seals they were investigating
  - 2. (11) with notes on seals - much written in shorthand
  - 3. notes by Arthur J. Edwards about seals
  - 4. notes by A.W. Greeley about seals, 1897
- List of treaties possibly affecting the Aleutians and Bering Sea. 2 pp. 1969. (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Photographs of seal rookeries on St. Paul Island and St. George Island, 1891-1897 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Photographs of seal rookeries on St. Paul Island, 1892-1897 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Photographs of seal rookeries on St. Paul Island, 1892-1897 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Photographs of seal rookeries on St. Paul Island, 1892-1896 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Photographs of seal rookeries on St. Paul Island, 1892-1895;with images of the village of Petropaulski Kanchatka, beach on Copper Island, and Canadian sealing schooner on the Bering Sea (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Scenes in China (interpositive images from nitrate negatives) (Box 5, Folder 6)